hi this is a feature video presentation
in this series what is the Magellan
course and in this video presentation we
are going to look at the highest levels
of ego development as described from
Suzanne Cook orators work now before we
get into looking at these levels as she
describes it I want to make a caveat and
that is from a linear perspective
development suggests that the new forms
will come from the people or the
individuals that have achieved the
highest forms but from an evolutionary
spec perspective that is rarely the case
from a evolutionary perspective
the highest or most mature forms of the
current trajectory are usually dead ends
in that the new forms branch out from
earlier forms so as we look at this
video of the highest forms that have
been described by developmental theory
the highest forms of cognitive and ego
development this is not to suggest that
in the very individuals at the stage
will be the individuals or the group of
individuals that will carry on into the
trajectory of the new form and again if
we look at the evolutionary record
that's rarely the case it's more often
the case that the new trajectory toward
the shift the evolutionary shift to a
higher structure or a novel structure
comes from a branching some prior forms
so with that caveat being said I hope
you enjoy this presentation of Suzanne
Cooke graters description of the higher
level
so the ego development as she can
describe them so the first highest level
the last two levels which she calls post
autonomous stages is called the
construct aware stage and she writes at
the construct aware stage there is a new
awareness of how language itself shapes
one's reality and for the first time the
boundaries the lines or boundaries one
has drawn can be seen that they are
arbitrary but useful distinctions
opposites can be embraced because one
realizes they necessitate each other so
this brings into the notion of the
identity of opposites she states the key
to deeper understanding is to find the
ground that encompasses and unifies them
both and this is very significant
because the word ground is intentionally
chosen I think because instead of saying
the key to understanding this
relationship here between opposites is
not to make the higher synthetic move
but to find the deeper ground that
encompasses and has unified them both
then at the next stage at the unitive
stage one knows that opposites represent
one underlying reality so there's no
longer search it's just knowing that the
struggle of opposites is a symptom of
our illusion that the boundaries we hold
are real thus the solution to the
struggle lies in the dissolving about
all boundaries even the boundary
between a map creating minds in our
experience of reality and so there's
this transparency that the maps that we
make to represent reality have these
boundaries and also create a boundary
between the map making activity in our
experience of reality for the unitive
person immediate experience with the
universe represents a freedom from the
tensions created by objectifying reality
in framing it in dualistic terms so this
is a very profound statement that there
can be for the unitive person an expedia
experience with the universe that is
free of the framing in objectified or
rarefied or abstract or conceptual terms
free of the framing of that in dualistic
terms and so for the Unity person the
unitive person understands that because
they can see or into it or be aware of a
reality that is non-dualistic they can
see that the dualistic aspect of reality
is constructed by the mind that frames
that reality or represents that reality
in dualistic terms so if we look at the
movement or the operations from
conventional to post conventional to
post autonomous or the highest stages
this is what Suzanne Kruger has to say
in conventional development conventional
development is the is constituted by the
frame of mind that is most attached to
rationality or this rational structure
of consciousness intends to defend
most against the intrusion of material
from either non-national whether it's
mythical or pre conventional sources or
for more integrated later perspectives
so the conventional mind the
conventional or standard mind cent set
of the rational structure what gaps are
called the mental structure is defends
itself against the suggestion that there
are there are other ways of knowing
whether they're their pre conventional
so mythical sources and influx or
whether they're post conventional if the
conventional mind accepts the
transpersonal personal at all it often
does so as a belief system or an
ideology and adheres to its letter and
mechanics rather than its spirits so the
conventional mind can accept in
quotations the concept of transpersonal
and how it works
how it can engineer problem-solving as
received knowledge because that's the
conventional mind can operate
abstractions in a systematic sort of way
without actually experiencing the
transpersonal realm in the post
conventional situation we see that the
post conventional mind reverses the
process of separation and
differentiation of earlier though ego
stages and this is very important to get
up up to the post conventional stage all
the moves the eagle has made is this
pattern of differentiation separation
differentiation more and more complex
integration to a higher level new
separation differentiation more more
complex integration at higher levels so
this is the progressive stage up the
development
but once you get to the post
conventional development this whole
process this whole dynamic of ego ego
making meaning reverses that process the
rigid boundaries between knower and
known are gradually deconstructed and
merged the dismantling occurs in two
steps one the dialectic or systemic view
and two the unitary stage or post
autonomous view to see reality as well
as the self as an interconnected whole
or system rather than as an aggregate of
separate well-defined elements is the
first step towards a more holistic view
of reality so in the dialectic stage or
systemic view we have systems thinkers
are aware of themselves as participant
observers who are inevitably part of the
problem space so this is a new
development their high stage development
they see that complex problems cannot be
solved by refining existing linear
scientific methods so they look toward
meta systemic or paradigmatic change
however they still believe in a
rationally knowable reality and rely and
logically derived solutions and
procedures and they do not yet
understand how profoundly humans are
conditioned by the language habit so
this is the stage at which people start
to reason and problems all systemically
and then meta systemically and then
paradigmatically and then cross paired
matically because they keep working the
system they keep working the system that
logically derive solutions and
procedures and so they hyper complexify
the problem because they cannot get
underneath they cannot get underneath
the conditions of thought itself so
here's a little sidebar when we look at
the actual models of cognitive
development we see they are limited by
the cognitive capacities of the
theorists and the researcher in the
philosopher themselves
so from Piaget who was a simple linear
structuralist through pastiches who sees
development as dialectical to even the
great meta sistema can cause
paradigmatic thinkers like Commons and
Fisher's to the post autonomous view of
cook writer we see that they include
more and more and more of a
developmental territory at the higher
levels depending upon the level that
their models are operating on the higher
stages in the system's view remain
wedded to symbolic codification purely
cognitive models do not realize the
incommensurability between symbol and
that which is symbolized the models do
not recognize the limit limits of
rational analysis and of symbolic
representation and thus cannot discover
the hidden assumptions in paradoxes they
they enact in their own models so here
is a short couple of videos of Suzanne
kegerator talking about this move into a
post autonomous stage
whatever I've relied on so far somebody
is somewhat suspicious I mean to come to
an integration and say that's fine
that's one of the many ways of how I can
leave and so when you're doing that
you're actually operating from a space
where you can see your own perspectives
yes and where you can enter the Eagle
and say okay I'm playing this game of
that game or or I'm written the sink of
the games I'm playing and also the
genuine efforts and struggles and all of
that it's thrilling discovery isn't it
the first time yes sir yeah that's right
and also it is Derby long because well
now or can you stand on in all small
Denise um you start questioning some of
the cultural assumptions but not yet the
fundamental you still believe that with
language and enough methods and all that
you will figure out what's going on are
you saying in postmodern yes at this
more complex than we thought but now you
say there's nothing I can do it's really
nothing to hold on so now then when you
watch automatically can't be helped us
devotion a spirit you have transcendent
moments and anything hard or something
else something totally else anew if you
want to direct it well new paradigm
before it was differentiation
integration solving a very regular
pattern more and more complex higher and
higher levels of perspectives and now
something totally different
in the post autonomous stages we have
the construct aware person who begins to
reject the overall stance of the systems
thinker who becomes aware of the
profound splits inherent in rational
flop who becomes conscious of the
linguistic process of splitting into
dualistic opposites unconsciously
experiences the egos machination and
self-preservation processes so there's a
turning in of awareness of how this
whole thing works you've been on this
path of reconciling opposites only to
exchange them for other opposites the
dualistic mind keeps dancing and dancing
and dancing this whole pattern of
movement toward higher levels becomes
completely transparent to the construct
aware person through turning into and
observing their own mental processes the
construct aware person can spontaneously
discover a direct mode of experiencing
where no are unknown momentarily merge
and the personal self sense disappears
and she becomes conscious of the
difference between symbol and the
underlying phenomenon it symbolizes and
so the use of
language becomes very specific with the
construct aware person so the constructs
aware person becomes aware and works
toward accepting language that language
has worked to do that language is
pointing out underlying phenomenon and
sure other people you could always point
out the antithesis for the antithetical
or the dialectical aspect of the
statement but the construct aware
persons is trying to work hard to show
you that language is doing something
it's pointing to the underlying
phenomenon and you can play with it in a
dialectical or polarity or dualistic
framework but the constant the way a
person works toward designing language
that is less susceptible to toying with
it that way so that it is more
successful in doing the work of pointing
to the underlying phenomenon and at this
point the what Suzanne recorder has
found is that the construct aware a
person first of all they're relatively
isolated there's not a lot of people
that they can interact with that this at
this level and there are problem
existential problems that arise with
this level of awareness and there's
usually two responses to it according to
her research there's two responses to
the predicament of realizing the
futility of creating objective artifacts
from a need to make permanent and
substantive that which is in flux and
immaterial and so the two responses
she's categorized into the more
rationally inclined constructor where a
person remains indebted to and tries to
perfect conscious discursive rationality
whereas the more intuition directed
person is drawn to move beneath or
beyond discursive rationality at all the
more rationally inclined person then
valiantly constructs an ever more
precise account in real time of their
complex and dynamic theories about how
the world in their minds work only to
deconstruct them as soon as they become
aware of doing so whereas the more
intuition directed persons yearn deeply
to make the transpersonal experience
permanent wanting to be free of the
judging mind and the endlessly
categorizing and labeling experience
wishing to simplify to wishing to simply
witness life as in unfolds in Contra
distinction to these two responses if
they reach the unitive stage people
learn to accept reality as is showing a
tolerance of continuous change can
embrace polar opposites on an affective
level and not just cognitively and are
open to ongoing experience and have
deeper empathy for all beings people at
the unitive stage are more at ease with
a fluid open-ended self-identity with
not knowing who they are